Shah Rukh Khan: Be it Mumbai or Delhi, Chennai or Kolkata,
无论是孟买还是德里，是金奈还是加尔各答，
all our big cities have one great thing in common,
我们所有的大城市都有一个共同点，
they happily welcome people from  smaller places arriving in search of work.
这些大城市都欢迎外地人来找工作，
What is also true is that this warm welcome leads to consequences.
但这如此温暖的欢迎也会带来许多危机。
Problems like housing in these cities are born.
像是住房紧缺的问题也随之而来。
Today we have with us a human settlement expert and researcher: Dr. Gautam Bhan,
今天，人居环境专家和研究者古塔姆巴汗教授将为我们分享
who is re-imagining a solution to this increasing problem.
对于这一日益严峻的问题的解决方法，
He will share with us the new picture of urban India that he can see.
他会为我们分享他眼中创新的印度城市蓝图，
TED Talks India New Thoughts welcomes Dr. Gautam Bhan.
欢迎来到印度版《TED Talks 新点子》，让我们欢迎古塔姆·巴汗教授。
Dr. Gautam Bhan, everyone.
古塔姆·巴汗教授，欢迎！
(Applause)
（掌声）
Gautam Bhan: In this country, until a few years ago,
在印度，不知从几年前起，
if you asked someone:
如果你问某人：
"Where are you from?"
“你来自哪里？”
the answer would be Delhi, Mumbai, Kolkata.
他们都会回答德里，孟买，加尔各答。
You'd immediately ask again:
然后你马上就会问：
"Where do you belong?"
“那你是属于哪里呢？”
Until recently in India, nobody was from a city;
在不久之前，还没有多少人是真正来自这些城市；
people only migrated to the city.
他们多半是迁移于此。
This is changing.
这是一大改变。
Urbanization is changing India,
城市化正在改变着印度，
but are our cities prepared?
但是我们的城市准备好应对这一改变了吗？
Let's assume you were born somewhere else.
我们假设你是出生于别处，
Your parents worked as laborers all day.
你的父母在城里打工，
Then you too would have come to a city for progress.
所以你随父母搬到了大城市，
Or maybe, like it happens today, you were born in the city itself.
或者就像今天发生的，你就恰巧出生在了大城市，
One day you go out looking for an accommodation in the city,
总有一天，你要独立地在城市中寻找属于自己的住所，
to buy or maybe just to rent.
去买房，或者只是租房。
Will you be able find an affordable home?
你能够找到一个你负担得起的家吗?
The government says we are falling short of at least 20 million homes.
政府说我们还缺少至少 2000 万间住所，
20 million homes, that's 100 million people.
2000 万个住所，那就是 1 亿的人民的家。
And this is not the shortage of 3 BHKs (bedroom hall kitchen).
这不是说只缺 3 BHKs （三室一厅一厨房格局），
95 percent of the shortage is for people earning 10 to 15,000 rupees per month.
95% 的住房短缺针对的是每月收入10到15000卢比的人。
Will you be able to find an affordable home in this budget?
这笔预算能让你找到一个负担得起的家吗?
If this happened with you, what would you do?
如果这发生在你身上，你会怎么做?
Home is not a car or some sort of jewellery.
我说的家，不是一辆车，更不是首饰珠宝，
Home is food and clothes.
家是能吃得饱、冻不着的地方，
Nobody can live without it.
没有人能居无住所。
If you couldn't find a home in a city to either buy or rent,
如果你不能在城市里找到一个家，不管是买还是租，
you too would be driven to do what most people end up doing.
你就不得不去做大部分人必须做的事，
Make a home wherever possible.
不管怎么样都要寻找一个容身之处。
You too would make a settlement.
你也要有一个落脚的地方，
The government may keep calling it a slum,
政府称之为贫民窟，
but like the people living there,
但就像那些住在里面的人，
I too will call it a settlement.
我会把它称之为聚居地。
One hundred million are not homeless.
这一亿人民不是无家可归，
They have homes.
他们有家，
Homes they built on their own.
他们靠自己的双手创造的家，
But most of these homes are in settlements.
但是其中大多数家只能算是个聚居地。
This is the truth of an affordable home in India.
在印度，这就是“可负担的家”的真相。
The homes in settlements are cheap, but not sturdy.
这些聚居地很便宜，设施却很简陋。
The homes outside are sturdy, but not cheap.
外面世界的家很完美，却一点也不便宜。
(Applause)
（掌声）
We will have to lay the foundation of a new thought from here itself.
从这里开始，我们要为新点子埋下种子。
A settlement is not a problem; it is a solution.
聚居地不应该变成一个问题，而应该成为一个解决的办法。
We just have to make it secure and sturdy.
我们要做的仅仅是让它们变得安全而坚固。
To fulfill the shortage of 20 million homes
为了填补这 2000 万短缺的住房，
you cannot make 20 million 25 square foot flats,
你没法创造出 2000 万间25平方英尺的公寓，
and neither should you be making them.
你也不应该去建造它们。
For example take the Karnataka government.
就拿卡纳塔克邦政府为例，
They have a very good record in this.
他们就在这方面做出了很好的表率。
By 2020, Karnataka needs 2.6 million homes.
到 2020 年，卡纳塔克邦需要 2600 万个住所，
In the last ten years they have managed to make 350,000 homes.
在过去的十年里，他们只完成了 35 万个住房。
Even if a government tries with complete sincerity,
即使政府带着解决问题的诚意，
it cannot fulfill this need in the next couple of lifetimes.
这个目标还是遥不可及。
If we do not make new homes,
如果我们不去创造新的聚居地，
then what is the next solution?
那下一个解决之策又能是什么呢？
How to make a settlement secure?
怎样才能让这些聚居地变得安全起来？
Firstly, eviction needs to be stopped.
首先，先停下无休止的驱逐，
Bulldozing needs to be stopped.
强制拆除的方案也应该停下。
Never has that resulted in progress in the past,
这些都是无用功，
nor will it in the future.
无论是在过去还是未来。
(Applause)
（掌声）
We have to start believing that the laborers who build and run the city
我们必须坚信，因为有了这些劳动力，我们的城市才得以运转，
have a right over the land of that city.
而他们在城市里也应当拥有属于自己的权利。
(Applause)
（掌声）
I know you are thinking
我知道你们一定在想，
that settlements are made on illegally captured land,
这些贫民窟都是非法占用土地，
but capturing of land never happens in the dead of the night.
但是别忘了，没人会在死气沉沉的夜晚去偷窃土地。
Whether the land belongs to the government or not,
不论这块地是不是属于政府，
a settlement is never formed secretly.
一个聚居地从来不是悄悄地出现的。
It is inhabited over time.
它是长久以来一直有人居住着的。
The government also agrees that
政府也一直默认它们的存在，
the settlements in our cities have been there for over 10, 20, 30, even 40 years.
这些聚居地至少在大城市里存在了 10 年、20 年、30 年，甚至40年。
What kind of illegally captured land is this,
这算是什么非法占用土地，
which was ignored for 30 years
可以被忽视 30 年之久，
and suddenly a day before eviction is declared illegal?
然后忽然在驱逐的前一天被认定是非法占用土地？
A settlement can easily accommodate 15 to 60 percent of a city's population
一个小小的聚居地足以容纳我们城市 15%-60% 的人口，
by using just one, two or maximum ten percent of the land.
它需要的仅仅是 1%、2% 或是最多10%的土地。
Can such a huge number of people not have a right over this small bit of land?
为什么这么多人民连拥有如此小小一片土地的权利都没有呢?
A city's progress is often measured by the cost of its land.
一个城市的发展往往以一片土地的价值来衡量，
How do you ascribe a cost to the life of a person living on a piece of land?
但是你又该如何衡量一片土地能给予一个人容身之处的价值呢？
A settlement is not asking you for shiny homes;
一个聚居地不意味着要你去建一个豪华的家；
all it's asking for is basic necessities:
它只不过是可以提供正常生活的必须条件：
electricity, roads, water, toilets and drainage.
水电，道路，厕所和下水道。
We call this upgradation.
我们称之为设施改善。
Here's an example of upgradation.
举一个设施改善的例子：
In Ahmedabad, they started a program
在艾哈迈达巴德，他们启动了一个项目，
where for ten years, 44 settlements were promised there wouldn't be any eviction.
这个项目保证十年之内 44 个聚居地不会受到驱逐的威胁——
Only a promise.
这仅仅只是一个保证，
Nothing written, no documents.
没有记录，更没有存档——
And basic necessities were provided to them.
然后提供给那里的人们基础生活必需品。
In ten years that slum changed into a locality, a place, a world of its own.
十年以后，这个贫民窟变成了一个地区、一个属于他们自己的世界，
The government didn't have to build even a single new home.
而政府完全不需要去为他们建一个新家了。
(Applause)
（掌声）
Thailand launched this program at national scale,
泰国在全国范围内启动了这个项目，
benefiting 100,000 people in 137 cities.
137 个城市里的十万人民因此受益。
And every person was given the right to live over that land.
每一个人都拥有了在这片土地上生活的权利。
But pay attention here.
但请注意，
Not the right to sell, but the right to live there,
不是去出售这片土地的权利，仅仅是能居住在这里的权利，
use it, settle on it.
使用它，居住的权利。
The whole world knows now that to move forward,
全世界现在都知道要进步，
we cannot remove settlements.
我们或许不能清除贫民窟，
We can only advance when we think of ways to make settlements secure and sturdy.
我们却可以想办法让这些地方变得安全而坚固。
But just one thing.
但还有一件事，
If we know it, then why doesn't it happen?
如果我们知道了，那为什么没能实现？
To apply this new thinking to settlements,
为了让这一新的设想实现，
we, that is you and me, need to look deep within and get rid of the disgust, disrespect and apprehensions that we have.
我们，也就是你们和我，都需要了解并摆脱心中那些厌恶、不敬和恐惧的态度，
Actually I should not be standing here in front of you today.
我甚至觉得今天我都不应该站在这里，
A person from the settlement who lives there should be standing here.
真正应该站在这里的应当是一个生活在那里的人。
But if someone like that came here, you wouldn't have listened to him.
但是如果真的是那样的话，我觉得你们甚至都不像听他讲了。
You are listening to me, because you think I am not from a settlement.
你们听我讲，因为你们觉得我不是来自聚居地，
This is the very thought that needs to be changed.
这就是我们需要去改变的想法。
Thank you.
谢谢大家。
(Applause)
（掌声）
SRK: Thank you very much. Thank you, Dr. Gautam Bhan.
沙鲁克汗：非常感谢您。谢谢您，古塔姆·巴汗教授。
Thanks a lot.
非常感谢。
Please tell me, you just gave an example of Thailand
请你告诉我，你刚刚为我们分享了泰国的例子。
and the big thing there is
最精彩的部分是，
the homes are for people to settle in, not to sell.
家不应该是为了出售，而是为了提供容身之所。
They cannot be used for sale.
它们的存在不应该是为了出售。
Is there a similar thought process or program in our country too,
那么在印度是不是也有相似的项目
inspired by your talks and those of people around you?
是受到了你和你身边的人的启发？
GB: I wouldn't say by me,
古塔姆：我不会说只是因为我，
but by the people movement who are fighting for rights in the city.
我会说是受到了为这城市里的人权奋斗的无数人的启发，
That is making a difference.
是他们实现了这种改变。
For instance, in Odisha the Chief Minister, Mr. Patnaik, announced the same scheme:
比如，奥里萨邦的首席部长普提尼卡先生就宣布了同样的策略：
that all the people in settlements will have rights over that land.
在聚居地生活的人们应当拥有对土地的权利。
(Applause)
（掌声）
And I think this scheme shouldn't be called populism;
我觉得这样的设想不应该被称为平民主义；
it should be called an economic development strategy.
而是应当被视为经济发展策略。
Because economic development does not happen from the top, but from the bottom.
因为经济的发展不是自上而下的，恰恰相反，它来自于人民基本生活的改善。
(Applause)
（掌声）
SRK: I too promise
沙鲁克汗：我也在此保证，
I will only say settlements, and not slums, ever again. 100 percent.
我以后绝对不再称聚居地为贫民窟。100% 保证。
(Applause)
（掌声）
Dr. Bhan you came here and said such wonderful things.
巴汗教授，你来到这里，带来了如此精彩的演讲。
There is a song. I will not sing it, as I am a terrible singer.
有这样一首歌——我唱歌很难听，所以我不会唱。
GB: I too am a terrible singer.
古纳姆：我也唱得很差。
SRK: But we can't keep shut also, because we are saying wonderful things.
沙鲁克汗：但是我们不会闭嘴的，因为这段歌词非常美好。
(laughter)
（笑声）
So we will just say it.
所以我们还是说出来吧。
Slowly the heart will find settlement.
慢慢地，心会找到归宿。
GB: Slowly the heart will find settlement.
古纳姆：慢慢地，心会找到归宿。
SRK: Only then will life be filled with love and fun times.
沙鲁克汗：只有那一刻生活才充满了爱和喜悦。
(Applause)
（掌声）
Ladies and gentlemen, Dr. Gautam Bhan. Thank you.
女士们，先生们，感谢古纳姆·巴汗教授！
(Applause)
（掌声）